Appendix THE PRINCIPLES OF NEWSPEAK Newspeak was the official language of
Oceania and had been devised to meet the ideological needs of intock or English Socialism.
In the year 1984 there was not as yet anyone who used news speakers his sole
means of communication, either in speech or writing.
The leading articles in the Times were written in it but this was a tour de
force which could only be carried out by a specialist.
It was expected that Newspeak would have finally superseded old speak or Standard
English, as we should call it) by about the year 2050..
Meanwhile it gained ground steadily, all Party members tending to use news-speak
words and grammatical constructions more and more in their everyday speech.
The version in use in 1984, and embodied in the 9th and 10th Editions of the
Newspeak Dictionary, was a provisional one, and contained many superfluous words
and archaic formations which were due to be suppressed later.
It is with the final, perfected version, as embodied in the 11th Edition of the
Dictionary, that we are concerned here.
The purpose of Newspeak was not only to provide a medium of expression for the
world view and mental habits proper to the devotees of insock but to make all
other modes of thought impossible.
It was intended that when Newspeak had been adopted once and for all and all
speak forgotten, a heretical thought— —that is, a thought diverging from the
principles of insock should be literally unthinkable, at least so far as thought
is dependent on words.
Its vocabulary was so constructed as to give exact and often very subtle
expression to every meaning that a Party member could properly wish to express,
while excluding all other meanings and also the possibility of arriving at them
by indirect methods.
This was done partly by the invention of new words, but chiefly by eliminating
undesirable words and by stripping such words as remained of unorthodox meanings,
and so far as possible of all secondary meanings whatever.
To give a single example. The word free still existed in Newspeak, but it could
only be used in such statements as 'This dog is free from lice' or 'This field is
free from weeds'.
It could not be used in its old sense of 'politically free' or 'intellectually free',
since political and intellectual freedom no longer existed even as concepts, and
were therefore of necessity nameless.
Quite apart from the suppression of definitely heretical words, reduction of
vocabulary was regarded as an end in itself there's no word that could be
dispensed with was allowed to survive.
Newspeak was designed not to extend but to diminish the range of thought, and
this purpose was indirectly assisted by cutting the choice of words down to a minimum.
Newspeak was founded on the English language as we now know it, though many
new speak sentences, even when not containing newly created words, would be
barely intelligible to an English speaker of our own day.
Newspeak words were divided into three distinct classes, known as the A
vocabulary, the B vocabulary (also called compound words), and the C vocabulary.
It will be simpler to discuss each class separately, but the grammatical
peculiarities of the language can be dealt with in that section devoted to
the A vocabulary, since the same rules held good for all three categories.
The A vocabulary.
The A vocabulary consisted of the words needed for the business of everyday life—
—for such things as eating, drinking, working, putting on one's clothes, going
up and down stairs, riding in vehicles, gardening, cooking, and the like.
It was composed almost entirely of words that we already possess words like hit,
run, dog, tree, sugar, house, field— —but in comparison with the present-day
English vocabulary the number was extremely small, while their meanings
were far more rigidly defined. All ambiguities and shades of meaning had
been purged out of them.
So far as it could be achieved, a new speak word of this class was simply a
staccato sound expressing one clearly understood concept.
It would have been quite impossible to use the A vocabulary for literary
purposes or for political or philosophical discussion.
It was intended only to express simple, purposive thoughts,
usually involving concrete objects or physical actions.
The grammar of Newspeak had two outstanding peculiarities. The first of
these was an almost complete interchangeability between different parts of speech.
Any word in the language (in principle is applied even to very abstract words such
as if or when) could be used either as a verb, noun, adjective or adverb.
Between the verb and the noun form, when they were of the same root, there was
never any variation, this rule of itself involving the destruction of many archaic forms.
The word thought, for example, did not exist in Newspeak. Its place was taken by
think, which did duty for both noun and verb.
No etymological principle was followed here: in some cases it was the original
noun that was chosen for retention, in other cases the verb. Even where a noun
and verb of kindred meaning were not etymologically connected, one or other of
the most frequently suppressed.
There was, for example, no such word as cut, its meaning being sufficiently
covered by the noun verb knife.
Adjectives were formed by adding the suffix full to the noun verb and adverbs by adding -wise.
Thus, for example, speedful meant 'rapid' and speed wise meant 'quickly'.
Certain of our present-to-day adjectives, such as good, strong, big, black, soft, were
retained, but their total number was very small.
There was little need for them, since almost any adjectival meaning could be
arrived at by adding full to a noun- verb.
None of the now existing adverbs was retained, except for a very few ending in -wise: the
-wise determination was invariable.
The word well, for example, was replaced by good wise In addition, any word— —this again applied
in principle to every word in the language— —could be negative by adding the FX on
or could be strengthened by the affix plus-, or, for still greater emphasis double Plus
Thus, for example, uncold meant 'warm', while Plus Cold under double Plus Cold
meant, respectively, 'very cold' and 'superlatively cold'.
It was also possible, as in present-day English, to modify the meaning of almost
any word by prepositional affixes such as anti-post up-, down-, etc. By such methods
it was found possible to bring about an enormous diminution of vocabulary.
Given, for instance, the word good, there was no need for such a word as bad, since
the required meaning was equally well— —indeed, better— —expressed by ungood.
All that was necessary, in any case where two words formed a natural pair of
opposites, was to decide which of them to suppress.
Dark, for example, could be replaced by unlight, or light by undark, according to preference.
The second distinguishing mark of Newspeak grammar was its regularity.
Subject to a few exceptions which are mentioned below, all inflections followed the same rules.
Thus, in all verbs the preterite and the past participle were the same and ended in -ed.
The predator of Steel was steeled the preterative think was thinked, and so on
throughout the language, all such forms of swam, gave, brought, spoke, taken, etc.,
being abolished. All plurals were made by adding s or -es as the case might be.
The plurals of man, ox, life, were man's ox's lives Comparison of adjectives was invariably
made by adding er, -est (good goodest), irregular forms and the
more, most formation being suppressed.
The only classes of words that were still allowed to inflict irregularly
were the pronouns, the relatives, the demonstrative adjectives and the auxiliary verbs.
All of these followed their ancient usage, except that whom had been scrapped
as unnecessary, and the shell showed tenses had been dropped, all their uses
being covered by will and wood There were also certain irregularities
in word formation arising out of the need for rapid and easy speech. A word
which was difficult to utter, or was liable to be incorrectly heard, was held
to be obso fact of a bad word: occasionally therefore, for the sake of
euphony, extra letters were inserted into a word or an archaic formation was retained.
But this need made itself felt chiefly in connection with the B vocabulary.
Why so great an importance was attached to ease of pronunciation will be made
clear later in this essay.
The B vocabulary.
The B vocabulary consisted of words which had been deliberately constructed
for political purposes: words, that is to say, which not only had
in every case a political implication, but were intended to impose a desirable
mental attitude upon the person using them.
Without a full understanding of the principles of insock it was difficult to
use these words correctly.
In some cases they could be translated into Old speak or even into words taken
from the A vocabulary, but this usually demanded a long paraphrase and always
involved the loss of certain overtones.
The B words were a sort of verbal shorthand, often packing whole ranges of
ideas into a few syllables, and at the same time more accurate and forcible
than ordinary language.
The B words were in all cases compound words compound words such as speak right were
of course to be found in the a vocabulary but these were merely
convenient abbreviations and had no special ideological color
They consisted of two or more words, or portions of words, welded together in an
easily pronounceable form.
The resulting amalgam was always a noun verb and inflected according to the ordinary rules.
To take a single example: the word good think meaning, very roughly, 'orthodoxy', or,
if one chose to regard it as a verb, 'to think in an orthodox manner'.
This inflected as follows non-verb good think past tense and past participle good things
present participle good thinking adjective good thinkful adverb good
think wise verbal noun good thinker The B words were not constructed on any etymological plan.
The words of which they were made up could be any parts of speech, and could
be placed in any order and mutilated in any way which made them easy to
pronounce while indicating their derivation.
In the word crime think thought crime for instance, the think came second,
whereas in thinkpole Thought Police) it came first, and in the latter word police
had lost its second syllable.
Because of the great difficulty in securing euphony, irregular formations
were commoner in the B vocabulary than in the A vocabulary.
For example, the adjective forms of miniature mini packs and mini love were,
respectively many truthful many peaceful and many lovely simply because truthful
pactful and -loveful were slightly awkward to pronounce.
In principle, however, all B words could inflict and all inflected in exactly the same way.
Some of the B words had highly subtleized meanings, barely intelligible
to anyone who had not mastered the language as a whole.
Consider, for example, such a typical sentence from the Times leading article
as old thinkers unbelief feelingsok The shortest rendering that one could make
of this in Old speak would be: 'Those whose ideas were formed before the
Revolution cannot have a full emotional understanding of the principles of English Socialism.'
But this is not an adequate translation.
To begin with, in order to grasp the full meaning of the new speak sentence quoted
above, one would have to have a clearer idea of what is meant by yingsok
And in addition, only a person thoroughly grounded in ingstock could appreciate
the full force of the word belly feel which implied a blind, enthusiastic
acceptance difficult to imagine today; or of the word old zinc which was
inextricably mixed up with the idea of wickedness and decadence.
But the special function of certain Newspeak words, of which old think was
one, was not so much to express meanings as to destroy them.
These words, necessarily few in number, had had their meanings extended until
they're contained within themselves whole batteries of words which, as they
were sufficiently covered by a single comprehensive term, could now be scrapped and forgotten.
The greatest difficulty facing the compilers of the new speak Dictionary
was not to invent new words, but, having invented them, to make sure what they
meant: to make sure, that is to say, what ranges of words they canceled by their existence.
As we have already seen in the case of the word free, words which had once borne
a heretical meaning were sometimes retained for the sake of convenience, but
only with the undesirable meanings purged out of them count as other words such as honor
justice, morality, internationalism, democracy, science and religion had simply ceased to exist.
A few blanket words covered them, and, in covering them, abolished them.
All words grouping themselves around the concepts of liberty and equality, for
instance, were contained in the single word crimethink, while all words grouping
themselves around the concepts of objectivity and rationalism were
contained in the single word old think Greater precision would have been
dangerous. What was required in a Party member was an outlook similar to that of
the ancient Hebrew who knew, without knowing much else, that all nations other
than his own worshiped false gods'. He did not need to know that these gods were
called Bal Osiris molok asteroth and the like: probably the less he knew about
them the better for his orthodoxy.
He knew Jehovah and the commandments of Jehovah: he knew, therefore, that all gods
with other names or other attributes were false gods. In somewhat the same way,
the Party member knew what constituted right conduct, and in exceedingly vague generalized
terms he knew what kinds of departure from it were possible.
His sexual life, for example, was entirely regulated by the two news-speak words
sex crime sexual immorality) and good sex chastity sex crime covered all sexual misdeeds
whatever. It covered fornication, adultery, homosexuality and other perversions, and,
in addition, normal intercourse practiced for its own sake.
There was no need to enumerate them separately, since they were all equally
culpable, and, in principle, all punishable by death.
In the C vocabulary, which consisted of scientific and technical words, it might
be necessary to give specialized names to certain sexual aberrations, but the
ordinary citizen had no need of them.
He knew what was meant by good sex that is to say, normal intercourse between man
and wife, for the sole purpose of begetting children, and without physical
pleasure on the part of the woman: all else was sex crime
In Newspeak it was seldom possible to follow a heretical thought further than
the perception that it was heretical: beyond that point the necessary words were non-existent.
No word in the B vocabulary was ideologically neutral.
A great many were euphemisms.
Such words, for instance, as joycamp forced labor camp) or mini packs Ministry
of Peace that is Ministry of War) meant almost the exact opposite of what they appeared to mean.
Some words, on the other hand, displayed a frank and contemptuous understanding of
the real nature of Oceanic society.
An example with Pro feed meaning the rubbishy entertainment at spurious news
which the Party handed out to the masses.
Other words, again, were ambivalent, having the connotation Goodwin applied to the
Party and 'bad' when applied to its enemies.
But in addition there were great numbers of words which at first sight appeared
to be mere abbreviations and which derived their ideological color not from
their meaning but from their structure.
So far as it could be contrived, everything that had or might have
political significance of any kind was fitted into the B vocabulary.
The name of every organization or body of people, or doctrine, or country, or
institution, or public building, was invariably cut down into the familiar
shape; that is, a single easily pronounced word with the smallest number of
syllables that would preserve the original derivation.
In the Ministry of Truth, for example, the Records Department, in which Winston
Smith worked, was called Rick Depp the Fiction Department was called fikodep
the teleprograms Department was called Teledep, and so on.
This was not done solely with the object of saving time.
Even in the early decades of the 20th century, telescoped words and phrases had
been one of the characteristic features of political language; and it had been
noticed that the tendency to use abbreviations of this kind was most
marked in totalitarian countries and totalitarian organizations
Examples were such words as Nazi, Gestapo come in turn in Precor hajit prop
In the beginning the practice had been adopted as it were instinctively, but in
Newspeak it was used with a conscious purpose. It was perceived that in thus
abbreviating a name one narrowed and subtly altered its meaning, by cutting
out most of the associations that would otherwise cling to it.
The words Communist International, for instance called up a composite picture
of universal human brotherhood, red flags, barricades, Karl Marx and the Paris
Commune. The word commentone on the other hand, suggests merely a tightly knit
organization and a well-defined body of doctrine refers to something almost as easily
recognized and as limited in purpose, as a chair or a table
come in turn is a word that can be uttered almost without taking thought,
whereas Communist International is a phrase over which one is obliged to
linger at least momentarily.
In the same way, the association's called up by a word like miniature were fewer
and more controllable than those called up by Ministry of Truth.
This accounted not only for the habit of abbreviating whenever possible,
but also for the almost exaggerated care that was taken to make every word easily pronounceable.
In Newspeak, euphony outweighed every consideration other than exactitude of meaning.
Regularity of grammar was always sacrificed to it when it seemed necessary.
And rightly so, since what was required, above all for political purposes, were
short-clipped words of unmistakable meaning which could be uttered rapidly
and which roused the minimum of echoes in the speaker's mind.
The words of the B vocabulary even gained in force from the fact that
nearly all of them were very much alike.
Almost invariably those words good think mini packs Pro feed sex crime Joy Camp
insock belly feel thinkpole and countless others— —were words of two or
three syllables, with the stress distributed equally between the first syllable and the last.
The use of them encouraged a gabbling style of speech, at once staccato and monotonous.
And this was exactly what was aimed at.
The intention was to make speech, and especially speech on any subject not
ideologically neutral, as nearly as possible independent of consciousness.
For the purposes of everyday life it was no doubt necessary, or sometimes
necessary, to reflect before speaking, but a Party member called upon to make a
political or ethical judgment should be able to spray forth the correct opinions
as automatically as a machine gun spraying forth bullets.
His training fitted him to do this, the language gave him an almost foolproof
instrument, and the texture of the words, with the harsh sound and a certain
willful ugliness which was in accord with the spirit of ingzock assisted the
process still further.
So did the fact of having very few words to choose from.
Relative to our own, the Newspeak vocabulary was tiny, and new ways of
reducing it were constantly being devised.
Newspeak, indeed, differed from most all other languages in that its vocabulary
grew smaller instead of larger every year.
Each reduction was again since the smaller the area of choice, the
smaller the temptation to take thought.
Ultimately it was hoped to make articulate speech issue from the larynx
without involving the higher brain centers at all.
This aim was frankly admitted in the Newspeak word duck speak meaning 'to quack like a duck'.
Like various other words in the B vocabulary duck speak was ambivalent in meaning.
Provided that the opinions which were cracked out were orthodox ones, it
implied nothing but praise, and when the Times referred to one of
the orators of the Party as a double-plus good duck speaker it was
paying a warm and valued compliment.
The C vocabulary.
The C vocabulary was supplementary to the others and consisted entirely of
scientific and technical terms.
These resembled the scientific terms in use today, and were constructed from the
same roots, but the usual care was taken to define them rigidly and strip them of
undesirable meanings. They followed the same grammatical rules as the words in
the other two vocabularies.
Very few of the C words had any currency either in everyday speech or in political speech
in his scientific worker or technician could find all the words he needed in
the list devoted to his own specialty but he seldom had more than the
dismantling of the words occurring in the other lists.
Only a very few words were common to all lists, and there was no vocabulary
expressing the function of Science as a habit of mind, or a method of thought,
irrespective of its particular branches.
There was, indeed, no word for 'Science', any meaning that it could possibly bear
being already sufficiently covered by the word insock From the foregoing account it will be
seen that in Newspeak the expression of unorthodox opinions, above a very low
level, was well now impossible.
It was of course possible to utter heresies of a very crude kind, a species of blasphemy.
It would have been possible, for example, to say Big Brother is ungood.
But this statement, which to an orthodox here merely conveyed a self-evident
absurdity, could not have been sustained by reasoned argument, because the
necessary words were not available.
Ideas inimical to wingstock could only be entertained in a vague wordless form,
and could only be named in very broad terms which lumped together and
condemned whole groups of heresies without defining them in doing so.
One could, in fact, only use Newspeak for unorthodox purposes by illegitimately
translating some of the words back into world speak For example, All mans are equal was a
possible Newspeak sentence, but only in the same sense in which All men are
RedHead is a possible old speak sentence.
It did not contain a grammatical error, but it expressed a palpable untruth that
is that all men are of equal size, weight or strength.
The concept of political equality no longer existed, and this secondary
meaning had accordingly been purged out of the word equal.
In 1984, when old speak was still the normal means of communication, the danger
theoretically existed that in using Newspeak words one might remember their original meanings.
In practice it was not difficult for any person well grounded in a double thing
to avoid doing this, but within a couple of generations even
the possibility of such elapse would have vanished.
A person growing up with news speakers his soul language would no more know that equal had once
had the secondary meaning of 'politically equal', or that free had once met
intellectually free then for instance, a person who had never heard of chess
would be aware of the secondary meanings attaching to queen and rook.
There would be many crimes and errors which it would be beyond his power to
commit, simply because they were nameless and therefore unimaginable.
And it was to be foreseen that with the passage of time the distinguishing
characteristics of Newspeak would become more and more pronounced— —its words
growing fewer and fewer, their meanings more and more rigid, and the chance of
putting them to improper use always diminishing.
When old speak had been once and for all superseded, the last link with the past
would have been severed.
History had already been rewritten, but fragments of the literature of the past
survived here and there, imperfectly censored, and so long as one retained
one's knowledge of old speaker it was possible to read them.
In the future such fragments, even if their chance to survive, would be
unintelligible and untranslatable.
It was impossible to translate any passage of old speaker to Newspeak
unless it either referred to some technical process or some very simple
everyday action, or was already orthodox Good thankful would be the new speak
expression) in tendency.
In practice this meant that no book written before approximately 1960 could
be translated as a whole.
Pre-revolutionary literature could only be subjected to ideological translation—
—that is, alteration incense as well as language.
Take for example the well-known passage from the Declaration of Independence:
We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they
are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable Rights, that among
these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness. That to secure these rights,
Governments are instituted among Men, deriving their powers from the consent of the governed.
That whenever any Form of Government becomes destructive of those ends, it is
the Right of the People to alter or abolish it, and to institute new Government....
It would have been quite impossible to render this into Newspeak while keeping
to the sense of the original.
The nearest one could come to doing so would be to swallow the whole passage up
in the single word crime think A full translation could only be an ideological translation,
whereby Jefferson's words would be changed into a panaderic on absolute government.
A good deal of the literature of the past was, indeed, already being transformed in this way.
Considerations of prestige made it desirable to preserve the memory of
certain historical figures, while at the same time bringing their achievements
into line with the philosophy of insock Various writers, such as Shakespeare,
Milton, Swift, Byron, Dickens and some others were therefore in process of translation:
when the task had been completed, their original writings, with all else that
survived with the literature of the past, would be destroyed.
These translations were a slow and a difficult business, and it was not
expected that they would be finished before the first or second decade of the 21st century.
There were also large quantities of merely utilitarian literature—
—indispensable technical manuals, and the like— —that had to be treated in the same way.
It was chiefly in order to allow time for the preliminary work of translation
that the final adoption of Newspeak had been fixed for so later date as 2050.
end of 1984 by George Orwell